[Music]
in this section we're going to cover two routing algorithms that are widely used
in practice in today's internet for computing a path from a given source to
a given destination the first is known as a link state algorithm the second
is known as a distance vector algorithm
and although they share the same common
goal of computing
shortest path or at least cost path what
we'll see is they differ
very much in the way in which they
actually compute these shortest paths
the goal of any routing algorithm is to
determine a good
path or a good route or a good route
between a source node
and a destination node through a network
of routers
to understand routing algorithms we're
going to need to unpack that statement a
little bit
what do we mean by a path what is a path
through a network of routers
and also what does it mean to be good
what does it mean for a root to be good
or one root to be better than another
root
so let's define a path as a sequence of
routers that packets traverse
from a given initial source host to the
final destination host
we see a path here from this source host
on the left to this destination host on
the bottom right
passing through these five routers and
implicit in a path being a sequence of
routers
is the sequence of links connecting the
routers in the path
these links are going to be important as
we'll see in just a sec
and what do we mean by good well could
mean a lot of different things
maybe it's the least cost path maybe
it's the fastest path
maybe it's the least congested path as
we'll see the definition of cost and the
definition of good
is going to be left up to the network
operator
and let me add here before we dive into
routing algorithms that routing is
definitely a top 10 networking challenge
we'll use a graph abstraction a concept
that's familiar to
any undergraduate computer science
student has taken a data structures
course or an algorithms course
to describe a routing algorithm so a
graph consists of a set of
n nodes these might correspond to the
routers within the network
these end nodes are connected by edges
or
links and each of these links has an
associated cost
the link cost between nodes a and b
denoted c
sub a b is the cost of the direct link
connecting
a and b for example the cost between
links w
and z here denoted c sub w z is
five the cost between x and y for this
link
the cost is one link costs can be
different in each direction or be the
same as in this case here
and lastly the link costs between two
nodes that are not directly connected is
going to be infinity
for example the link cost between u and
z which are not directly connected
is infinity now where do these costs
come from
well the routing algorithm or protocol
doesn't really care
but in practice it's defined by the
network operator
the cost could be one in which case the
lease cost path algorithm is the
shortest path
or the cost could be inversely related
to the bandwidth the higher the
bandwidth the lower the cost
or the cost could be directly related to
a link's congestion level their queuing
delay
the higher the congestion level the
higher the cost
we're going to look at two routing
algorithms in just a second
but broadly we can classify routing
algorithms any routing algorithm
according to whether
they're global or decentralized and
whether they're static or
dynamic in a global algorithm the
algorithm has
complete network-wide information about
network topology and
all link costs algorithms with global
state information are sometimes referred
to
as link state algorithms since the
algorithm has to be aware
the cost of each and every link in the
network
dijkstra's algorithm is an example of a
global link state algorithm
in a distributed or decentralized
routing algorithm the calculation of the
leaks cost
path is carried out in an iterative
distributed manner by the routers
no router has complete information about
the costs of all network links
instead each router begins with the
knowledge of the cost of its own
directly attached links so just its
local neighborhood
and then through an iterative process of
calculation
and exchange of information with its
immediately neighboring nodes
a node iteratively calculates the least
cost path to a set of destinations
the bellman ford algorithm will study is
an example of a distributed algorithm
also known as a distance vector
algorithm since it
iteratively computes a vector of
currently known least cost to all
network nodes
routing algorithms can also be
classified as static
or dynamic or quasi-static based on the
time
scale at which they operate and iterate
we're now ready to take a look at
dijkstra's link state
routing algorithm and i know if you're a
student who's taken an algorithms course
like compsci 311
here at the university of massachusetts
you know you've seen dijkstra's
algorithm
isn't it great to know that the
algorithm that you learned in a theory
course is actually being used in
practice
can almost guarantee you that the
packets that are being transferred to
you now as part of this video
were almost certainly routed to you
using dijkstra's link state routing
algorithm
dykstra's link state routing algorithm
is a centralized algorithm
because it assumes that the complete
network topology
and all the link costs in the network is
known to the node that's making the
calculation
the algorithm itself is going to compute
the least cost paths from
one node which we'll call the source
node to all other nodes in the network
and you can see how this then gives rise
to a forwarding table
for that node dijkstra's algorithm has
this very nice property it's iterative
and
after k iterations we're going to know
the least cost
path to the closest or least cost k
destinations and here's a notation that
we're going to use
we'll let c sub a b be the direct link
cost between nodes a
and b if nodes a and b aren't connected
this cost is going to be infinity so
it's just the one hop
direct link cost between two directly
attached nodes
d sub a is the current estimate of the
cost
of the least cost path from the source
to destination a
as we'll see d sub a is going to be
iteratively updated for all destinations
a as the algorithm precedes p sub a is
what's
called the predecessor node along the
path from the source to node a
and finally n prime is the set of nodes
whose least cost
path is definitely known at this point
in the calculation
now let's take a look at the pseudo code
for dijkstra's link state routing
algorithm
the easy part is the initialization what
we're going to do is we're going to
initialize
n prime remember n prime is the set of
nodes whose least cost paths are known
from the source node u
we're going to initialize n prime to
just contain the source node u
and for all other nodes a within the
network and if a is directly attached to
u
then d sub a is going to just equal that
one hop
cost the cost from node u to a otherwise
d sub a is going to be infinity
okay that's the initialization easy
enough steps
8 through 15 are the heart of the
algorithm and this is just a loop
what we're going to be doing in the loop
each time we're going to find
one node a we're going to add it to n
prime
and we're going to do an update and then
we're going to iterate
back again so this loop has basically
two parts finding a node and then
performing an
update let's take a look at it now in
steps 9 and 10
we're finding a node a that's not in n
prime so this is a node
whose least cost path is not
definitively known
and we'll find the a not in m prime such
that d
sub a is a minimum and then we're going
to add it to n prime
remember once the node's added to n
prime it's in there for good because we
absolutely know the shortest path
to get to a so that's the identification
step within the loop
and then we've got an update step which
we see here in steps 11 and 12.
so the update step is the following
we're going to update
d sub b for all nodes in the network
b that are next to that is to say
adjacent
directly connected to a and not yet in  prime and here's the update step we're
n prime and here's the update step we're
going to say d sub b is equal to the minimum well of the
old value of d sub b and a potential new cost the new potential
cost is the minimum cost to get to a remember this is now known
plus the one hop cost to get from a to b
once we perform this update step for all
nodes b
that are adjacent to a we loop back and
we'll find a new
a and so we start off again at step
eight
and we continue this looping process
adding one node
a into n prime each time until
all the nodes in the network are in n
prime
probably the easiest way to understand
dijkstra's algorithm is to take a look
at an
example so let's do that next so on the
bottom left here you see the network on
which
we want to run dijkstra's algorithm
there are six nodes and the links shown
here along with the associated link
costs
the source node from which we're going
to be computing all the least cost paths
is node u on the far left hand side here
well let's start off with the
initialization step since that's the
easiest
remember the initialization step says
for all nodes a
if a is adjacent to this source node u
then d sub a is equal simply to the cost
the one
hop direct link cost of getting from u
to a and so let's take a look here we
can see here that the direct neighbors
of nodes u
are v w and x and so you can see on the
first line here the cost to get to v
is 2 cost to get to w the direct cost to
get to w
is 5 and the direct cost to get to x
is 1. and we've filled in the
predecessor node simply to say
that the predecessor to nodes v w
and x the shortest path from u
is actually node u itself nodes y and z
are initialized to infinity because they
don't have a direct one hop connection
to source node u
and so now it's time to jump into our
first pass through the loop
steps 8 9 and 10. and in steps 9 and 10
we're going to do a node identification
we want to find the node a
that's not yet in n prime such that
d sub a the distance the cost to a is a
minimum
and then we're going to add a into n
prime so taking a look at the table
above we see the cost of b is 2 the cost
of w
is 5 the cost to x is 1.
so x is the minimum here we're going to
add node
x into n prime and you can see on the
bottom left here on the graph we've
drawn a little red arrow to show that to
get from u to x
that's a direct connection there now
let's proceed on to the update step and
this is shown in step 11 here
and the way we're going to update dcb is
shown here
the new value of d sub b is going to be
the minimum of the old value of d
sub b or the cost to get to a
d sub a plus the direct cost to get from
a to b
again the logic here is that we want to
update the cost to b
knowing well it can't be more than the
old cost to b
but now we know the minimum cost to a
and we know
the direct cost from a to b so we want
to add those two together
and that would give us the cost to b
going through
a and we're going to take the minimum of
those two values
so you can see here shown in gray we
update the values of d sub v
d sub w and d sub y
and as you can see the new cost for dw
and dy are now less the cost to get to w
has gone down from five to four and the
cost to get to y
has gone down from infinity now down to
two
so we're going to update those values in
the table above
and then iterate back to the beginning
of the loop
well now we've completed two rows in the
table and we're back at the beginning of
the loop again
so we're at the identification step
let's find the node a
that's not yet an n prime that has a
minimum value of d
sub a looking at the table above we can
see
that node y which has a cost of 2
and node v also has a cost of 2. we can
break that tie
arbitrarily let's choose y so we'll add
y into the set n prime
now we move on to the update step given
that we've added
y into a prime this is step 11.
what we want to do again here is we want
to update d sub b
for all b that are adjacent to y in this
case
and not yet in n prime you see the
update formula here
well let's take a look at why we just
added y in
and y has two neighbors that are not yet
in  prime that's w and z
n prime that's w and z
so we're going to update the values of w and z as shown here
and you can see that the new cost to w is now decreased from
four to three and the new cost to get to z has decreased from
infinity to 4. so we update the table above and we're ready to iterate
again well we're entering the loop again at step 8 for the third time
and again we start with an identification step let's find the node a that's
not in n prime yet such that d sub a is a minimum and
as we scan across the row that we computed in step 2 we see
that v is now a minimum at a cost
we see that v is now a minimum at a cost
of 2. so let's add v into the set and prime now that we've
done the identification step the next step is going to be the update step
again and now we want to update d sub b for all nodes that
are adjacent to this new node v that we just added into n prime
you see the update formula there let's take a look at node v down
here that we just added in well what are the neighbors that are not
yet in n prime that are directly attached to v well use in it
already x is in it already but
use in it already x is in it already but
w is not in it so we update w as shown in the step
here shown in gray and we see that the cost to w hasn't changed
so we're all done with the update step
let's loop back again
and once we enter the loop again we
first do the identification
let's find a node not in n prime such
that d sub a is a minimum
well there's only two nodes left that
aren't in n prime
w and z w has the smaller cost of three
rather than z's cost of four
so we're going to add w into n prime
we're going to perform an
update step once again you can see the
update step well the only node whose
cost needs to be updated
is z so you see the step for updating
the cost of z
the value of d sub z doesn't change so
the table
remains the same we loop back again to
step eight
enter the identification step and we'll
find a node a
not in n prime such that d sub a is a
minimum well there's only one node left
that's z so we'll add z and and prime
and now there are no nodes left so
there's no update step
we exit the algorithm and we're all done
and now if you take a look at the
network in the bottom left hand side
you can see the least cost routing tree
from node u
to all other nodes in the network from
this
we're able to recover the forwarding
table specifically
from u if we want to get to destination
v
we go across this link here with a
direct cost of 2
otherwise if we want to get to x to y
to w or to z we're going to forward a
packet to x
because x is the next hop node on the
least cost
path from u to all of the destinations
x y w and z
well i hope that discussion of
dijkstra's algorithm has given you a
good idea of how a centralized
link state algorithm works and let's
wrap up our discussion here of
dijkstra's algorithm with a discussion
of its complexity
its computational complexity its message
complexity as well as a discussion
of a possible pathology now to think
about the computational complexity
note that we need to pass through that
loop from lines
6 through 11 n times and each time we go
through that loop we have to make a
worse case
in comparisons so that will give us an
order n
squared computational complexity
let's analyze the message complexity of
dijkstra's algorithm from the point of
view
the number of messages needed to
disseminate link state information
each router needs to broadcast its link
state information to n other routers
and there are broadcast algorithms which
are really pretty interesting
that only require of n link crossings to
disseminate
a broadcast message from one source to n
other nodes recalling that there are now
in sources
the overall message complexity to
disseminate link state
is therefore order n squared
and before wrapping up our discussion of
the link state algorithm
let's consider a really interesting
pathology that can arise
we haven't said much about link costs
but imagine now that link costs are
dynamic
reflecting the amount of load on a link
for example the higher the load
the higher the cost some of the earliest
routing algorithms in the arpanet
use just this kind of short-term
load-dependent link costs
we'll take a look at the example below
of simple network topology
where link costs are equal to the load
carried on the link
note that the costs are now different in
each direction on a link
let's assume that nodes b c and d each
want to route traffic
only to node a and b and d send a unit
of load destined to a
and c sends a small amount of load
epsilon to a
and suppose the initial routing is as
shown here on the far left
when the link state algorithm's next run
node c determines based on the link
loads and their fourth costs
that the counterclockwise path to a now
has a cost of 1
while the counterclockwise path to a
which should have been using
has a cost of 1 plus 2 epsilon now
c's least cost path to a is clockwise
similarly b determines that its new
least cost path to a
is also clockwise resulting in the
routing shown in the second figure
when the link state algorithm's next run
nodes b c and d
all detect now a zero cost path to a
in the counterclockwise direction and
all route their traffic to the
counterclockwise routes
the next time the algorithms run bc and  all see zero costs for clockwise
d all see zero costs for clockwise
routing therefore route their traffic clockwise and so on well this was just a
toy scenario but it reflects the fact that dynamic routing algorithms can be very
subtle and it was perhaps because of such issues that later routing algorithms tended
to shy away from defining costs based on short-term congestion or load levels well
that wraps up our discussion of dijkstra's centralized link state routing algorithm but we're
not done with routing algorithms yet because coming up next we're going to take
a look at a very different kind of algorithm  take a look at a distributed bellman  ford routing algorithm
[Music]  you